<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--based on Google Scholar template technical-report-with-abstract.xml-->
<articles>
	<article>
		<front>
			<publisher>
				<publisher-name>
					Utilika Foundation 
				</publisher-name>
				<publisher-loc>
					Seattle, Washington 
				</publisher-loc>
			</publisher>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Ambiguity Control in Human-Machine Multiagent Systems: State of the Art
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<year>
						2004
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://utilika.org/pubs/etc/ambigmas.html">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						A survey of efforts to solve problems of linguistic ambiguity in the development of increasingly global and agent-supported information systems. Ambiguity is a central obstacle to several requirements for successful communication in multiagent systems. Strategies for dealing with this obstacle include controlling (preventing) ambiguity, and resolving it. Control strategies are present in many traditional and recent disciplines regulating the use of natural and formal languages. Conditions (such as the cost of misunderstanding and the relative value of the time of the communicating parties) are enumerated that would be expected to determine whether control or resolution strategies are more effective.
					</p>
					<p>
						Ambiguity control can be distinguished by whether it is central or distributed, and by whether it controls semantic or structural ambiguity. Semantic ambiguity tends to be domain-specific and structural ambiguity domain-independent. Central systems tend to be more efficient with domain-independent problems. Thus systems that employ central control of structural ambiguity and distributed control of semantic ambiguity are plausible. Formal languages, interactive elicitation systems, and controlled natural languages are among the devices with which control of structural ambiguity during the production of utterances has been attempted. Predicate-logic-equivalent varieties of natural languages, some equipped with checking tools, have purportedly been able to represent large fractions of the meanings humans want to express, but this claim requires verification, and such languages also require users to learn that the sole denotations of their expressions are not always the most probable denotations of the same expressions in the languages from which they are derived. The concept of multilingual equivalent controlled languages remains almost unexplored. Further research could be fruitful on the human factors in the usability of controlled natural languages and other strategies of ambiguity control.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			technical-report 
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<publisher>
				<publisher-name>
					Utilika Foundation 
				</publisher-name>
				<publisher-loc>
					Seattle, Washington 
				</publisher-loc>
			</publisher>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Ambiguity: Some Bibliographical Notes
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool 
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan 
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<day>
						5 
					</day>
					<month>
						6 
					</month>
					<year>
						2005 
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://utilika.org/pubs/etc/ambib.html">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						Annotated bibliography of works on ambiguity. Works are classified by subtopic into these categories: concepts of ambiguity; universal and contingent ambiguities; dimensions, types, and relatives of ambiguity; and controlling ambiguity. 
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			technical-report 
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<publisher>
				<publisher-name>
					Utilika Foundation 
				</publisher-name>
				<publisher-loc>
					Seattle, Washington 
				</publisher-loc>
			</publisher>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Can Controlled Languages Scale to the Web?: Evaluation of the DLT Intermediate Language
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool 
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan 
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<year>
						2006
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://utilika.org/pubs/etc/ambigcl/evdlt.html">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						An exploration of 32 controlled natural languages, based on English and eight other languages, revealed one, the DLT Intermediate Language, that was designed for multidomain use and whose documentation gave sufficient instructions and examples to allow a domain author to translate a realistic range of Web content into it. A test of this language on a sample of sentences from Web documents in the health and human rights domains found it expressive enough to represent all sentences in the sample, with low structural ambiguity, but some structural and much semantic ambiguity remained that could interfere substantially with human and machine comprehension. 
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			technical-report 
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<publisher>
				<publisher-name>
					Utilika Foundation 
				</publisher-name>
				<publisher-loc>
					Seattle, Washington 
				</publisher-loc>
			</publisher>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						The Panlingual Camera Phone
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Hecko 
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Martin 
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Ogunmola 
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Kinsley 
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool 
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan 
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Wong 
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Tim 
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Woodman 
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Peter 
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<month>
						3
					</month>
					<year>
						2007
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlingual.org/devpilot/rev.html">
				</self-uri>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.cs.washington.edu/education/courses/cse490f/07wi/project_files/camera/devpilot/rev.html">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						Progress report on the design of a user interface for an application that would operate on a mobile camera phone. Increasingly high-fidelity prototypes have been implemented on paper, on the Web, and on one mobile device, with revisions based on user and expert evaluation of the prototype on the basis of realistic tasks. The interface design provides for multimedia (camera, stored-image, text, handwriting, etc.) input with language identification, text recognition, and translation into any language, to be performed collaboratively by the user, the device, remote servers, and a human-computation network.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			technical-report
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<publisher>
				<publisher-name>
					Utilika Foundation
				</publisher-name>
				<publisher-loc>
					Seattle, Washington
				</publisher-loc>
			</publisher>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Panlingual Dogfood
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<year>
						2006
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://utilika.org/pubs/etc/pandog/index.html">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						The idea of a linguistically diverse yet efficiently interactive world is becoming popular, but no plausible model for its realization has yet been described. I envision here a process that supports this goal with collaborative panlingual semantic standardization. The process is panlingual not only in its product but also in its operation, thus complying with the "eat your own dogfood" principle and using its product to make itself possible. It is also participatory and lexicocentric, as illustrated by "dogfood". I envision the process helping to panlingualize interactive services, including search, question answering, discussion, correspondence, and knowledge dissemination.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			technical-report
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<publisher>
				<publisher-name>
					Utilika Foundation
				</publisher-name>
				<publisher-loc>
					Seattle, Washington
				</publisher-loc>
			</publisher>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Paraphrasal and Truth-Conditional Disambiguation of Quantification: Which Works Better?
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<day>
						17
					</day>
					<month>
						3
					</month>
					<year>
						2007
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://utilika.org/pubs/etc/aa/index.html">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						The Semantic Web vision relies on authors creating disambiguated content, but the claim that they are willing and able to do so is in doubt. I addressed this doubt by conducting a pilot experiment on human satisfaction and efficacy in disambiguation tasks, with 47 subjects. I selected two "minimal" tasks, showing subjects ambiguous sentences--sentences with scopally ambiguous adverbial quantifiers, such as "almost always"--and asking them to select between representations of two alternative meanings of each sentence. One task was paraphrasal: Each representation was a paraphrase. The other task was truth-conditional: Each representation was a situation description. Each subject judged 25 sentences; half performed one of these tasks per sentence, and the other half performed both tasks on each sentence.
					</p>
					<p>
						Average subjects spent 30-40 seconds per sentence, achieved approximately 75% inter-task consistency, and gained efficiency but not quality over the 25 trials. The paraphrasal task was somewhat more enjoyed and was performed faster than the truth-conditional task, but the most dramatic effect was that performing the paraphrasal task and the truth-conditional task was much faster when they were presented in that order than when they were in the opposite order, and even faster than performing the truth-conditional task alone. The tasks appear to have exerted some bias on responses: Subjects tended more to agree on a sentence's meaning if they performed the same task than if they performed different tasks on it. Subjects' comments exhibited a wide range of attitudes, from excited discovery to frustrated confusion, toward the tasks.
					</p>
					<p>
						The results cast doubt on the doubt about human beings as disambiguators. Both paraphrasal and truth-conditional disambiguation appear to be viable, and perhaps efficiently combinable, methods. Further research can explore humans' trainability and incentivizability for disambiguation tasks and individual differences in task-type preferences and aptitudes.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			technical-report
		</article-type>
	</article>
</articles>
