<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--based on Google Scholar template book-chapter.xml-->
<articles xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<article>
		<front>
			<book-meta>
				<title-group>
					<book-title>
						Game Equilibrium Models IV: Social and Political Interaction
					</book-title>
				</title-group>
				<isbn>
					0387542280
				</isbn>
				<publisher>
					<publisher-name>
						Springer-Verlag
					</publisher-name>
				</publisher>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="editor">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Selten
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Reinhard
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<year>
						1991
					</year>
				</pub-date>
			</book-meta>
			<chapter-meta>
				<title-group>
					<chapter-title>
						The Distribution of Foreign Language Skills as a Game Equilibrium
					</chapter-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Selten
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Reinhard
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<fpage>
					64
				</fpage>
				<lpage>
					87
				</lpage>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/flsge-abs.html">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						Individuals make choices of which of the world's thousands of languages to learn, responding to opportunities and incentives associated with contact, prestige, schooling, earnings, productivity, and communication. In the long run, such choices not only respond to the distribution and characteristics of native and non-native speakers of languages, but also affect them.
					</p>
					<p>
						Like some prior theoretical models (Grenier, Lang), we investigate here a model of language-learning choices with a fixed distribution of native languages. Unlike them, however, our model (A) generalizes learning incentives beyond earnings, (B) permits not only two but an unlimited number of languages to exist, and (C) permits languages with native speakers and languages without native speakers to exist.
					</p>
					<p>
						In our model, every person has exactly one native language, so the world population can be partitioned into native-speaker communities, which we model as continua. The world is a continuum of players of a noncooperative normal-form game, each player's strategy being the set of additional languages learned. We consider only pure strategies.
					</p>
					<p>
						The players' payoffs are the net beneﬁts they derive from learning the languages that they learn (a communicative beneﬁt minus a learning cost). A player's communicative beneﬁt is proportional to the importance-weighted fraction of the world population sharing at least one language with the player, where the player's community assigns some importance to each member of the world population.
					</p>
					<p>
						A player's learning cost is the product of a linguistic factor (dependent only on the player's native and learned languages) and a personal factor (differentiating all members of a community).
					</p>
					<p>
						We show that a player's payoff is independent of the strategies of the other members of that player's own community, because those strategies cannot affect the subset of the world population sharing at least one language with the player. But a player can affect the payoff of another player in the same community indirectly, by affecting the choices of players in other communities.
					</p>
					<p>
						We show further that a strategy which is payoff-maximizing for two players in a community (given the combination of all other communities' players' strategies) is also payoff-maximizing for all other players in that community whose personal factors lie between those two players'. The corresponding empirical prediction is that those native speakers of language X who learn the same set of foreign languages will tend to be more similar in (dis)inclination and (in)ability to learn languages than fellow community members in general.
					</p>
					<p>
						We further show that in any community-wide combination of payoff-maximizing strategies ("group best reply") the two factors of the learning cost are negatively associated, with players learning more expensive sets of languages being those who incur lower learning costs. The greater the linguistic factor, the greater the communicative benefit. Moreover, and perhaps counterintuitively, the greater the linguistic factor, the greater the payoff. A corresponding empirical prediction is that those who learn more difﬁcult sets of languages get higher proﬁts, despite the difﬁculty of the languages they learn.
					</p>
					<p>
						We move on to prove, by examining aggregated games, that it is possible for every player to adopt a best reply at the same time, i.e. that at least one equilibrium point exists.
					</p>
					<p>
						We discuss further empirical insights in light of numerical examples of our model. The examples illustrate tendencies for those who learn non-native languages to choose the most widely spoken ones, for members of small language communities to learn foreign languages more than members of large communities, for few persons to learn auxiliary languages (those without native speakers), even if they have relatively low learning costs, and for language communities with chronically poor second-language-learning abilities to enjoy above-average welfare levels.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</chapter-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			book-chapter
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<book-meta>
				<title-group>
					<book-title>
						Language Policy and Political Development
					</book-title>
				</title-group>
				<isbn>
					978-0-89391-611-4
				</isbn>
				<publisher>
					<publisher-name>
						Ablex Publishing
					</publisher-name>
				</publisher>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="editor">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Weinstein
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Brian
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<year>
						1990
					</year>
				</pub-date>
			</book-meta>
			<chapter-meta>
				<title-group>
					<chapter-title>
						Language Regimes and Political Regimes
					</chapter-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<fpage>
					241
				</fpage>
				<lpage>
					261
				</lpage>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/langpolreg.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						Linguistic activists use political variables to affect linguistic outcomes, and political activists use linguistic variables to affect political outcomes. Language regimes and political regimes can be characterized according to some identical attributes, including nationalism, modernity, centralization, egalitarianism, radicality, and populism. Beliefs in the necessary alignment of language regimes and political regimes along these dimensions are common but dubious.
					</p>
					<p>
						Predictions that changes in language regimes will cause analogous changes in political regimes, or vice-versa, are plausible, but often inconsistent and unpersuasive, partly because the evidence for them typically is based on single analytical strategies rather than more robust combinations of strategies. Another predictive fallacy is to assume that static associations between linguistic and political variables imply corresponding dynamic causation. Though wrong, such fallacious beliefs drive much policymaking and thus cause expectations to be disappointed. Commonly static information tends to be construed to support racist, sexist, nationalist, and classist ideas, as well as the idea of linguistic assimilationism.
					</p>
					<p>
						The terms used in characterizations of language regimes, such as “official language”, “minority language”, and “efficiency”, are usually undefined or vaguely defined. The vagueness is often deliberate. Making terms precise permits improved discussion, criticism, and prediction. Among the benefits are formalizations of language and political regime interactions into simple models that represent hypothetical mechanisms. One such model illustrates an argument that the preference space for language regimes is multidimensional and vulnerable to cycles of collective preferences.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</chapter-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			book-chapter
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<book-meta>
				<title-group>
					<book-title>
						Interlinguistics: Aspects of the Science of Planned Languages
					</book-title>
				</title-group>
				<isbn>
					0899255485
				</isbn>
				<publisher>
					<publisher-name>
						Mouton de Gruyter
					</publisher-name>
				</publisher>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="editor">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Schubert
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Klaus
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<year>
						1989
					</year>
				</pub-date>
			</book-meta>
			<chapter-meta>
				<title-group>
					<chapter-title>
						Linguistic Artificiality and Cognitive Competence
					</chapter-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Grofman
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Bernard
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<fpage>
					145
				</fpage>
				<lpage>
					156
				</lpage>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/lacc.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/lacc.txt">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						The hypothesis that artificial human languages are inevitably impoverished and that the use of such languages for the formulation of problems therefore impairs the reasoning of persons who attempt to solve those problems was investigated experimentally. One hundred thirty-five persons bilingual in English and the artificial language Esperanto were tested with two reasoning problems by questionnaire, administered on-site at a conference. One problem tested deductive reasoning, and the other tested the consistency of judgment under uncertainty. Each subject received one problem in English and the other in Esperanto, with the assignment of languages to problems randomized. The results of the deductive-reasoning test provided support for the hypothesis, with about 50% of the Esperanto responses correct and about 70% of the English responses correct. The results of the consistency test provided evidence against the hypothesis, with aggregate inconsistency 50% greater in English than in Esperanto. Possible explanations for the observed differences include the more formulaic and less intuitive competence in non-native languages, and evaluative and risk-tolerance associations of movement-oriented languages.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</chapter-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			book-chapter
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<book-meta>
				<title-group>
					<book-title>
						Advances in the Sociology of Language, Volume 2: Selected Studies and Applications
					</book-title>
				</title-group>
				<isbn>
					9027923027
				</isbn>
				<publisher>
					<publisher-name>
						Mouton
					</publisher-name>
				</publisher>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="editor">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Fishman
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Joshua A.
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<year>
						1972
					</year>
				</pub-date>
			</book-meta>
			<chapter-meta>
				<title-group>
					<chapter-title>
						National Development and Language Diversity
					</chapter-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<fpage>
					213
				</fpage>
				<lpage>
					230
				</lpage>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/ndld-asl.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						The joint distribution of domestic language diversity and GDP per capita is highly nonlinear, with almost no high-diversity prosperous countries. Does this support the hypothesis that language diversity impedes economic development?
					</p>
					<p>
						Data on the size, as a fraction of the population, of the largest native-language group, and the gross domestic product per person per year, were collected for 133 countries. The static relationship between these variables was represented graphically with a scatterplot. The distribution of bivariate values was found to be highly nonlinear, and describable as a dispersion of countries throughout three quadrants of the bivariate space. The quadrant in which almost no countries were located was that with the upper half of GDP and the lower half of largest-language share. In other words, there were almost no highly linguistically diverse, prosperous countries. Although this result is sensitive to the definitions of the variables, some plausible redefinitions would apparently strengthen rather than weaken it. The result appears to support assertions that linguistic diversity is a barrier to economic development, but such a conclusion would be premature, because the distribution of values does not demonstrate an effect, nor, if there is an effect, its directionality.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</chapter-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			book-chapter
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<book-meta>
				<title-group>
					<book-title>
						The Fergusonian Impact
					</book-title>
				</title-group>
				<isbn>
					0899252141
				</isbn>
				<publisher>
					<publisher-name>
						Springer-Verlag
					</publisher-name>
				</publisher>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="editor">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Fishman
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Joshua A.
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="editor">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Clyne
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Michael
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="editor">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Abdelaziz
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Mohamed
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="editor">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Tabouret-Keller
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Andrée
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="editor">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Krishnamurti
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Bh.
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<year>
						1986
					</year>
				</pub-date>
			</book-meta>
			<chapter-meta>
				<title-group>
					<chapter-title>
						Optimal Strategies in Linguistic Games
					</chapter-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<fpage>
					157
				</fpage>
				<lpage>
					171
				</lpage>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/oslg.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						The basic concepts of the theory of games are introduced and their relevance to choices made about languages described. The use of game models in the development of the theory of language behavior is illustrated with a basic model of a bilingual conversation game, in which two bilinguals, each of whom has as a second language the other's native language, choose which languages to use in successive moves of a conversation. It is shown that in a two-move game without coordination the outcome produced by the players' use of their self-interest-maximizing strategies is in some cases deficient: worse for both players than an outcome they might have negotiated. If the ability to make binding promises is introduced, in some cases a player can, by making such a promise, make it rational for the other player to adopt a strategy different from the one that that player would otherwise rationally adopt. The model suggests some empirical predictions amenable to testing, such as that conversations between strangers will begin in the initiating party's native language more often than conversations between acquaintances, and alternation between languages will be more frequent in formal institutional conversations than in informal personal ones. Empirical evidence suggests additional motives beyond those introduced here could be usefully added for more realistic models, but that they would likely leave the conversation-initiating player with an advantage over the responding player.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</chapter-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			book-chapter
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<book-meta>
				<title-group>
					<book-title>
						Ethnic Russia in the USSR: The Dilemma of Dominance
					</book-title>
				</title-group>
				<isbn>
					978-0080237008
				</isbn>
				<publisher>
					<publisher-name>
						Pergamon Press
					</publisher-name>
				</publisher>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="editor">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Allworth
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Edward
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<year>
						1980
					</year>
				</pub-date>
			</book-meta>
			<chapter-meta>
				<title-group>
					<chapter-title>
						Whose Russian Language? Problems in the Definition of Linguistic Identity
					</chapter-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<fpage>
					237
				</fpage>
				<lpage>
					248
				</lpage>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/russlingid.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						The (subjective) identity of a language has ontological, associative, historical, and moral aspects. The rhetoric of language policy in the USSR reveals conflicts among these aspects and efforts to resolve them. Three major conflicts about Russian are (1) between its ontological and associative identities (what it is versus to whom it belongs), (2) between its historical and moral identities (its unique interethnic role versus linguistic equality), and (3) between the domestic and international aspects of its identity. Soviet theorists of linguistic identity mostly deny rather than seek to resolve these conflicts.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</chapter-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			book-chapter
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<book-meta>
				<title-group>
					<book-title>
						The Handbook of Language and Globalization
					</book-title>
				</title-group>
				<isbn>
					978-1-4051-7581-4
				</isbn>
				<publisher>
					<publisher-name>
						Wiley-Blackwell
					</publisher-name>
				</publisher>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="editor">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Coupland
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Nikolas
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<year>
						2010
					</year>
				</pub-date>
			</book-meta>
			<chapter-meta>
				<title-group>
					<chapter-title>
						Panlingual Globalization
					</chapter-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<fpage>
					142
				</fpage>
				<lpage>
					161
				</lpage>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/panglob.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						Globalization apparently promotes the death of small languages. Activists for linguistic diversity can pursue it, despite globalization, with at least four strategies: moral advocacy, economic incentives, political decentralization, and translation technology. This fourth strategy, and the challenges to its efficacy, are exemplified by the University of Washington and Utilika Foundation’s PanLex research project on panlingual lexical translation.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</chapter-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			book-chapter
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<book-meta>
				<title-group>
					<book-title>
						The Translator as Mediator of Cultures
					</book-title>
				</title-group>
				<isbn>
					978 90 272 2834 5
				</isbn>
				<publisher>
					<publisher-name>
						John Benjamins Publishing Company
					</publisher-name>
				</publisher>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="editor">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Tonkin
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Humphrey
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="editor">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Frank
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Maria Esposito
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<year>
						2010
					</year>
				</pub-date>
			</book-meta>
			<chapter-meta>
				<title-group>
					<chapter-title>
						Translators in a global community
					</chapter-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<fpage>
					73
				</fpage>
				<lpage>
					85
				</lpage>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/tgc/tgc.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						The popular yet paradoxical idea of a diverse global community raises questions about language and translation. Would a global community with a global language lose its other languages? Would a global community without a global language be able to interact efficiently across thousands of linguistic frontiers? One strategy that might make global community compatible with linguistic diversity is panlingual transparency via aspectual phased translation. With it, translators translate aspects of a discourse at each phase of a multiphase process, rather than translating the discourse in its entirety in a single act. In an initial simple model, communication in a global community relies on translation partitioned into four phases; the translation in each is either linguistic or cultural, but not both. A source discourse is translated culturally (within the source language), then linguistically (from the source language to a global representation), then linguistically (from the global representation to the target languages), then culturally (within the target languages). Such partitioning could elevate productivity by facilitating divisions of labor between professional and lay translators and between human and machine translators, and by letting monolinguals act as translators.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</chapter-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			book-chapter
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<book-meta>
				<title-group>
					<book-title>
						Advances in Language Planning
					</book-title>
				</title-group>
				<isbn>
					90 279 2618 2
				</isbn>
				<publisher>
					<publisher-name>
						Mouton
					</publisher-name>
				</publisher>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="editor">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Fishman
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Joshua A.
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<year>
						1974
					</year>
				</pub-date>
			</book-meta>
			<chapter-meta>
				<title-group>
					<chapter-title>
						Mass Opinion on Language Policy: The Case of Canada
					</chapter-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<fpage>
					481
				</fpage>
				<lpage>
					492
				</lpage>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/massopinionlp.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						A national survey of five thousand Canadian respondents in 1965 elicited opinions on language policy. The survey revealed substantial variation in support for concessions to the speakers of languages other than the respondents’, depending on the particular concession. Speakers of French were generally more acceptant of concessions to English than vice-versa. The English speakers most hostile to making concessions to French tended to be those with little or no French competence themselves and those living in places with few speakers of French.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</chapter-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			book-chapter
		</article-type>
	</article>
</articles>
