<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--based on Google Scholar template conference-article.xml-->
<articles xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<article>
		<front>
			<conference>
				<conf-name>
					International Workshop on Controlled Language Applications
				</conf-name>
				<conf-acronym>
					CLAW
				</conf-acronym>
				<conf-num>
					5
				</conf-num>
				<conf-date>
					<day>
						12
					</day>
					<month>
						8
					</month>
					<year>
						2006
					</year>
				</conf-date>
			</conference>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Can Controlled Languages Scale to the Web?
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/ambigcl/clweb.html">
				</self-uri>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://turing.cs.washington.edu/papers/pool-clweb.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.mt-archive.info/CLAW-2006-Pool.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						In a multilingual Semantic Web, authors might write in precise, expressive varieties of diverse languages. Do such controlled languages exist? Of 41 candidates, just 4 were (1) designed for multiple domains and genres and (2) documented enough for evaluation. A sample of Web statements on health and human rights revealed limited expressivity or precision in each language. The most expressive one avoided structural ambiguity but allowed semantic ambiguity that could frustrate human and machine comprehension. The possibility of a practical Web-scale controlled language remains undemonstrated but unrefuted.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			research-article
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<conference>
				<conf-name>
					K-CAP 2007: Fourth International Conference on Knowledge Capture
				</conf-name>
				<conf-date>
					<day>
						29
					</day>
					<month>
						10
					</month>
					<year>
						2007
					</year>
				</conf-date>
			</conference>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Disambiguating for the Web: A Test of Two Methods
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>
								Colowick
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								S. M.
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/aa/disamweb.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://turing.cs.washington.edu/papers/disambweb.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						The Semantic Web vision expects authors to represent knowledge unambiguously, but their ability and willingness to do so are contested. To evaluate experimentally two disambiguation methods that authors might use, we showed sentences from the Web containing syntactically ambiguous quantification to 386 subjects and asked them to choose between pairs of paraphrasal and/or truth-conditional restatements. The paraphrasal method was mostly superior. Subjects generally found both methods satisfying and were able to achieve substantial consistency and agreement.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			research-article
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<conference>
				<conf-name>
					Fachtagung Angewandte Soziolinguistik
				</conf-name>
				<conf-date>
					<day>
						19
					</day>
					<month>
						6
					</month>
					<year>
						1980
					</year>
				</conf-date>
			</conference>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						The Economics of Artificial Languages: An Exploration in Cost Minimization
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/eal.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/eal.txt">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						The use of artificial human languages would have economic effects. The use of such languages has been shown or argued to be less costly than the use of natural languages because of (1) a lower learning cost, (2) less costly translatability, (3) a greater facilitative effect of their learning on the subsequent learning of other languages, (4) the promotion of efficiencies in labor markets, and (5) the resulting political feasibility of decreases in the number and thus cost of official languages.
					</p>
					<p>
						This report analyzes one aspect of the economic difference between artificial and natural languages: their costs. In a binary matrix used as a model of the relevant universe, the rows are individuals and the columns are languages. The cell values are 1 when an individual knows a language and 0 when not. A communication matrix is derived from this language-knowledge matrix, representing the pairs of individuals with and without any shared language. Another matrix represents the cost that each individual would incur in order to learn each language. If we assumes interpersonally comparable and thus aggregatable costs, we can determine the total cost of each possible method (i.e. a combination of language-learning decisions) for making any set of individuals capable of any-to-any communication, and we can then determine which of these methods has the lowest cost. Formulas for these computations in an interpreted programming language are presented.
					</p>
					<p>
						Finally, these formulas are applied to a model of two natural languages and one artificial language. Each learning cost depends on interlingual distances, the number of languages an individual already knows, whether any of the languages already known is an artificial language, and whether the language to be learned is an artificial language. The computation determines the learnability that an artificial language requires in order to make a solution that relies entirely on that language the least-cost solution. Another result is a determination of the distances between the artificial language and natural languages that are compatible with the optimality of an artificial-only solution. It is shown that proximity between an artificial language and natural languages does not necessarily make an artificial-only solution more efficient; it may have the opposite effect.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			research-article
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<conference>
				<conf-name>
					International Symposium on Linguistic Human Rights
				</conf-name>
				<conf-date>
					<month>
						10
					</month>
					<year>
						1991
					</year>
				</conf-date>
			</conference>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						The Language Auction: A Nondiscriminatory Method of Choosing Official Languages
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								McFann
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Brian
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/auction.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						When plurilingual polities select official languages, it is often presumed that the disadvantages suffered by other languages' speakers are necessary and therefore justified. This necessity presumption has recently been theoretically challenged and has been disproven under limited conditions. It has been shown in principle that an interrogation-based decision rule can, by asking 2 questions, induce 2 self-interested language groups to disclose information that will always produce an efficient and nondiscriminatory policy selecting 1 or 2 official languages.
					</p>
					<p>
						We now describe another interrogation-based decision rule, taking the form of an auction mechanism, that has the same ability to discover an efficient and nondiscriminatory policy selecting official languages, but this rule is not restricted to 2 languages and 2 groups.
					</p>
					<p>
						The results provide additional theoretical evidence that efficiency and the subjectivity of linguistic preferences cannot excuse discrimination against language minorities.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			research-article
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<conference>
				<conf-name>
					The 23rd International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING 2010)
				</conf-name>
				<conf-date>
					<month>
						8
					</month>
					<year>
						2010
					</year>
				</conf-date>
			</conference>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						PanLex and LEXTRACT: Translating all Words of all Languages of the World
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Baldwin
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Timothy
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Colowick
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Susan M.
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/lextract.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						PanLex is a lemmatic translation resource which combines a large number of translation dictionaries and other translingual lexical resources. It currently covers 1353 language varieties and 12M expressions, but aims to cover all languages and up to 350M expressions. This paper describes the resource and current applications of it, as well as LEXTRACT, a new effort to expand the coverage of PanLex via semi-automatic dictionary scraping.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			research-article
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<conference>
				<conf-name>
					Multilingualism in Europe and the US: A Communications Challenge for Transatlantic Relations and Global Business
				</conf-name>
				<conf-date>
					<month>
						11
					</month>
					<year>
						1992
					</year>
				</conf-date>
			</conference>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Multilingualism versus Language Policy: Alternative Models for the EC
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/ecmodels.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						Many models can be applied to the design of a regime of official languages for the European Communities. These include a monarchic model, a synarchic model, an oligarchic model, a panarchic model, a hegemonic model, and a technocratic model. Each of these models can be optimal, depending on the criteria applied (including translation minimization, learning-cost minimization, or inequality minimization) and the facts, including how languages are distributed, how frequent translingual communication is, and how translators are paid.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			research-article
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<conference>
				<conf-name>
					Machine Translation Summit XII
				</conf-name>
				<conf-date>
					<month>
						8
					</month>
					<year>
						2009
					</year>
				</conf-date>
			</conference>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Lemmatic Machine Translation
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Soderland
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Stephen
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Lim
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Christopher
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Mausam
							</surname>
							<given-names>
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Qin
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Bo
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Etzioni
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Oren
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/auction.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://turing.cs.washington.edu/papers/SoderlandMTSummit09.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						Statistical machine translation is limited by reliance on large parallel corpora. We propose <i>Lemmatic MT</i>, a new paradigm that extends machine translation to a far broader set of languages, but requires substantial manual encoding effort.
					</p>
					<p>
						We present PANLINGUAL TRANSLATOR, a prototype Lemmatic MT system with high translation adequacy on 59% to 99% of sentences (average 84%) on a sample of 6 language pairs that Google Translate (GT) handles. GT ranged from 34% to 93%, average 65%. PANLINGUAL TRANSLATOR also had high translation adequacy on 27% to 82% of sentences (average 62%) from a sample of 5 language pairs not handled by GT.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			research-article
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<conference>
				<conf-name>
					SAAKM 2007: Semantic Authoring, Annotation and Knowledge Markup Workshop
				</conf-name>
				<conf-date>
					<day>
						28
					</day>
					<month>
						10
					</month>
					<year>
						2007
					</year>
				</conf-date>
			</conference>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Syntactic Disambiguation for the Semantic Web
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>
								Colowick
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								S. M.
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/aa/synsemweb.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://turing.cs.washington.edu/papers/synsemweb.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://sunsite.informatik.rwth-aachen.de/Publications/CEUR-WS/Vol-289/po02.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						Are people willing and able to disambiguate content for the Semantic Web? We asked subjects to use two methods (paraphrasal and truth-conditional selection) to disambiguate sentences from the Web. Native speakers did better with the paraphrasal method, and non-native speakers with the truth-conditional method. Unpaid volunteers performed better than paid subjects. Subjects' average disambiguation time was about 20 seconds per sentence.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			research-article
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<conference>
				<conf-name>
					Localization Industry Standards Association Berkeley Globalization Conference
				</conf-name>
				<conf-date>
					<day>
						5
					</day>
					<month>
						8
					</month>
					<year>
						2009
					</year>
				</conf-date>
			</conference>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Panlingual Localization
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/panloc.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						The goal of panlingual localization is to make any information instantly and freely accessible in any language. One strategy for achieving this goal is lemmatic communication, in which utterances are lemmatized before being translated, so that a panlingual dictionary, created from heterogeneous lexical resources and enhanced with translation inference, can more fully support the required translation. This concept is illustrated with a lemmatic user interface providing access to the PanLex project. Challenges facing this approach include incomplete data, mistranslation, inconsistency in the underlying data, and the limited intelligibility of lemmatic prose. These may be soluble, including with improvements in the quality and quantity of data and in the intelligence and interactivity of interfaces.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			research-article
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<conference>
				<conf-name>
					69a Universala Kongreso de Esperanto
				</conf-name>
				<conf-date>
					<month>
						7
					</month>
					<year>
						1984
					</year>
				</conf-date>
			</conference>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Lingviko, Politikiko kaj Ekblek
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/ekblek.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						Newspeak can be understood as a pair of positive answers to two unsettled questions: (1) Can states alter languages? (2) Can languages be altered in such a way that their speakers become unable to reason logically? The portrayal of Newspeak by Orwell suggests a further hypothesis, that the prevention of logical reasoning by means of language reform can also make permanent the control of the state by those currently in power. The features of Newspeak include regularity, simplicity, productivity (generality in inflection and derivation), and central governance.
					</p>
					<p>
						It is not obvious that a language with the features of Newspeak can function. If Esperanto, which does function, has the same features as Newspeak, then Esperanto provides empirical evidence for the feasibility of a Newspeak-like language. Esperanto does exhibit, to a substantial extent (but not completely), the features of Newspeak. If the speakers of Esperanto exhibited impaired logical reasoning, this impairment would provide evidence for the possibility of suppressing reasoning by means of language reform.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			research-article
		</article-type>
	</article>
</articles>
