<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--based on Google Scholar template journal-article.xml-->
<articles xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<article>
		<front>
			<journal-meta>
				<journal-title>
					Esperantic Studies
				</journal-title>
				<issn>
					1084-9831
				</issn>
				<publisher>
					<publisher-name>
						Esperantic Studies Foundation
					</publisher-name>
				</publisher>
			</journal-meta>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						The Challenge of Interlingualism
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Fettes
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Mark
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<month>
						4
					</month>
					<year>
						1998
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<volume>
					1998
				</volume>
				<issue>
					10
				</issue>
				<fpage>
					1
				</fpage>
				<lpage>
					3
				</lpage>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://esperantic.org/esf/ism.htm">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						We define an "interlingual" world as one that exhibits simultaneously high levels of linguistic diversity, linguistic integration, linguistic equity and linguistic efficiency. While its components are widely appreciated, there is doubt about their mutual compatibility and thus tolerance for the neglect of some as an alleged prerequisite for the achievement of others.
					</p>
					<p>
						Five major belief systems claim to offer approaches to making the world interlingual, or as interlingual as it can be. They are World English, Esperantism, Language Brokers, Plurilingualism, and Technologism. Progress in research on interlingualism would benefit from the clarification of these five systems, an examination of how they relate to each other, and empirical verification of the hypotheses that underlie them.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			research-article
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<journal-meta>
				<journal-title>
					Journal of Personality and Social Psychology
				</journal-title>
				<abbrev-journal-title>
					J Pers Soc Psychol
				</abbrev-journal-title>
				<issn>
					0022-3514
				</issn>
				<publisher>
					<publisher-name>
						American Psychological Association
					</publisher-name>
				</publisher>
			</journal-meta>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Coalition Formation in Small Groups with Incomplete Communication Networks
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<year>
						1976
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<volume>
					34
				</volume>
				<issue>
					1
				</issue>
				<fpage>
					82
				</fpage>
				<lpage>
					91
				</lpage>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/cfsg.txt">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						The question of how coalitions form within groups whose members cannot all communicate with each other was investigated with an experiment involving 41 adolescent West German subjects. In groups of six or seven members, subjects played a computer-based coalition game in which message channels were variably restricted to certain pairs of players. Subgroups with more communication channels became the winning coalition more often, and individual players voted more often to exclude from the coalition those with whom they could not communicate. Among those linked by communication channels, voting behavior was related to the frequency with which these channels were used and to the direction and content of the transmitted messages. For example, senders voted against receivers less than receivers voted against senders. The effects of the communication network remained undisturbed by two manipulations of the importance of communication.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			research-article
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<journal-meta>
				<journal-title>
					International Journal of the Sociology of Language
				</journal-title>
				<abbrev-journal-title>
					Int J Sociol Lang
				</abbrev-journal-title>
				<issn>
					0165-2516
				</issn>
				<publisher>
					<publisher-name>
						Mouton de Gruyter
					</publisher-name>
				</publisher>
			</journal-meta>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Language Planning and Identity Planning
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<year>
						1979
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<volume>
					1979
				</volume>
				<issue>
					20
				</issue>
				<fpage>
					5
				</fpage>
				<lpage>
					21
				</lpage>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/lpip.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						A network of 78 causal hypotheses about the interrelationships among 18 linguistic, identificational, communicational, affective, and cognitive variables is described as a directed graph. Elaborations of this network are required if it is to deal with strengths of relationships, multivariate relationships, inversions of relationships, modifications in groups and languages, and other complexities.
					</p>
					<p>
						Empirical tests of these hypotheses can reveal, or challenge the analyst to discover, influential contextual variables. For example, survey data from Wales and Canada indicate that in Wales a person's native language has a greater association with group identity than current language behavior does, but the opposite is true in Canada, even though in both countries current language behavior has an association with identity. The context of identity also seems to affect the strength of the language-identity association: If the context is ethnic, the association is considerably stronger than if the context is political in both those countries. But political identity, in the form of separatism, varies directly with linguistic Welshness and inversely with linguistic Frenchness. Competence in a minority language is also a better predictor of minority identity than competence in the majority language is a predictor of majority identity.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			research-article
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<journal-meta>
				<journal-title>
					International Journal of the Sociology of Language
				</journal-title>
				<abbrev-journal-title>
					Int J Sociol Lang
				</abbrev-journal-title>
				<issn>
					0165-2516
				</issn>
				<publisher>
					<publisher-name>
						Mouton de Gruyter
					</publisher-name>
				</publisher>
			</journal-meta>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Linguistic Exploitation
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<year>
						1993
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<volume>
					1993
				</volume>
				<issue>
					103
				</issue>
				<fpage>
					31
				</fpage>
				<lpage>
					55
				</lpage>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/lingexploit.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						Language is a tool of authority, so competitors for authority struggle over language. One tactic is to seek to define correctness. Despite popular demand for rules of linguistic correctness, politically inspired regulation of correctness in language may exceed that which serves the public interest.
					</p>
					<p>
						To investigate this possibility I define a simple formal model of a polity whose ruling class extracts wealth from its subject class, against resistance, and determines its own membership by defining the difficulty of the "language of rule", which all members of the ruling class must master. Rulers in this "linguistic regime" are assumed to vote for a more difficult or less difficult language of rule in accordance with a goal of personal wealth maximization.
					</p>
					<p>
						Under the model's assumptions, those who learn languages most easily become rulers. Despite the burden of mastering the language of rule, every ruler's wealth is at least as great as any subject's wealth. The ruling class never lets itself grow larger than it needs to be to compel universal subject compliance, and it may let itself disappear altogether. As it becomes more capable of compelling compliance, the ruling class makes the language of rule more difficult, and despite this a larger fraction of the population masters the language and joins the ruling class--something that would not happen if the ruling class had the power to regulate its size by fiat instead of linguistically.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			research-article
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<journal-meta>
				<journal-title>
					Journal of Theoretical Politics
				</journal-title>
				<abbrev-journal-title>
					J Theor Polit
				</abbrev-journal-title>
				<issn>
					0951-6298
				</issn>
				<publisher>
					<publisher-name>
						Sage Publications
					</publisher-name>
				</publisher>
			</journal-meta>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						The Multilingual Election Problem
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<month>
					1
					</month>
					<year>
						1992
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<volume>
					4
				</volume>
				<issue>
					1
				</issue>
				<fpage>
					31
				</fpage>
				<lpage>
					52
				</lpage>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/multielectprob.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						Multilingual elections may democratically enfranchise linguistic minorities, or may promote extremist, uncompromising, clientelistic, inefficient politics. One theoretical approach to this question extends existing spatial models of elections, allowing candidates to state different positions in different languages and assuming that language barriers give voters incomplete information about the positions stated in their nonnative languages.
					</p>
					<p>
						In a simple model of multilingual campaigning, candidates under some conditions can state different positions in different languages so that every voter aggregates the positions into a perception coinciding exactly with the voter's own position. To do this, candidates must choose positions more extreme than the positions of the respective audiences. As groups gain multilingual fluency, candidate extremism further increases. Extremism is vote-maximizing unless voters sufficiently penalize inconsistency. When inconsistency is important enough, candidates consistently take the position of the larger group in 2-group elections, and of the ideologically central group in 3-group elections.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			research-article
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<journal-meta>
				<journal-title>
					The American Political Science Review
				</journal-title>
				<abbrev-journal-title>
					Am Polit Sci Rev
				</abbrev-journal-title>
				<issn>
					0003-0554
				</issn>
				<publisher>
					<publisher-name>
						American Political Science Association
					</publisher-name>
				</publisher>
			</journal-meta>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						The Official Language Problem
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<month>
						6
					</month>
					<year>
						1991
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<volume>
					85
				</volume>
				<issue>
					2
				</issue>
				<fpage>
					495
				</fpage>
				<lpage>
					514
				</lpage>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/offlangprob-apsr1991.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/offlangprob.txt">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						Polities and organizations use and require particular languages for official business. The choice of official languages is a vexing issue. Theorists, convinced that a fair language policy cannot be efficient, have despaired of an elegant solution.
					</p>
					<p>
						To investigate this apparent dilemma, I mathematically model the problem of choosing an efficient and fair language policy for a plurilingual polity. The policy designates official languages, and it taxes the language groups to pay for translation among the official languages.
					</p>
					<p>
						Contrary to prevailing wisdom, this model implies that a fair language policy can be efficient. But what if language groups rationally misrepresent the costs of using a non-native official language? Even then, the policymaker can discover a fair language policy and, under some conditions, can use a cost-revelation procedure that discovers a fair and efficient language policy. The results challenge the claim that efficiency and practicality excuse the inferior treatment of language minorities.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			research-article
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<journal-meta>
				<journal-title>
					International Journal of the Sociology of Language
				</journal-title>
				<abbrev-journal-title>
					Int J Sociol Lang
				</abbrev-journal-title>
				<issn>
					0165-2516
				</issn>
				<publisher>
					<publisher-name>
						Mouton de Gruyter
					</publisher-name>
				</publisher>
			</journal-meta>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Optimal Language Regimes for the European Union
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<year>
						1996
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<volume>
					1996
				</volume>
				<issue>
					121
				</issue>
				<fpage>
					159
				</fpage>
				<lpage>
					179
				</lpage>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/optlangeu.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						Like other linguistically diverse institutions, the European Union promotes conflicting values as it chooses official languages. Increased activism and the admission of new states threaten a language-policy crisis. One approach to a solution is to analyze more carefully than before the universe of possible language regimes for institutions like the EU and the justifications for deeming any alternative “optimal”. We can define a language regime as a set of official languages and a set of rules permitting complete mutual comprehension in a “deliberation” among representatives of language groups. If only the groups' languages and one synthetic language are relevant, if the representatives are monolingual, if translators are bilingual, and if other simplifications are assumed, there are almost five times as many potentially optimal language regimes as language groups (e.g., with nine groups, 40). We can partition the language regimes into ten classes, distinguished by their official languages and whether they translate directly, via intermediate group languages, or via the synthetic language.
					</p>
					<p>
						The duration and urgency of the deliberation, the capacity of translation facilities, the importance of language equality, the distribution of group sizes, and the relative cost of learning the synthetic language are some conditions that determine which language regime is optimal. The prevailing conditions in the EU create a clear choice between two families of language regimes. One family satisfies the professed norm of equal language treatment by making either none or all of the groups' languages official. The other family, by making only the largest languages official, systematizes the common EU practice of sacrificing language equality for cost reduction. A victory for one normative position would favor a corresponding language regime, but a continued daily normative struggle would tend to produce complex variation in language regimes across EU agencies.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			research-article
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<journal-meta>
				<journal-title>
					Language Planning Newsletter
				</journal-title>
				<abbrev-journal-title>
					Language Planning Newsletter
				</abbrev-journal-title>
				<issn>
					0735-6552
				</issn>
				<publisher>
					<publisher-name>
						East-West Culture Learning Institute
					</publisher-name>
				</publisher>
			</journal-meta>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Some Observations on Language Planning in Azerbaijan and Turkmenistan
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<month>
						5
					</month>
					<year>
						1976
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<volume>
					2
				</volume>
				<issue>
					2
				</issue>
				<fpage>
					3
				</fpage>
				<lpage>
					6
				</lpage>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/lplan-aztkm.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						Professionals in language planning who were interviewed and observed in Azerbaijan and Turkmenistan in 1975 were enthusiastically engaged in the lexical enrichment and the standardization of their national languages and believed that their languages would in the future become more prestigious, more widely used, and more lexically autonomous from Russian than they were at that time.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			research-article
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<journal-meta>
				<journal-title>
					Politics and the Life Sciences
				</journal-title>
				<abbrev-journal-title>
					Polit Life Sci
				</abbrev-journal-title>
				<issn>
					0730-9384
				</issn>
				<publisher>
					<publisher-name>
						Association for Politics and the Life Sciences
					</publisher-name>
				</publisher>
			</journal-meta>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Thinking about the Optimal Number of Languages
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<month>
						8
					</month>
					<year>
						1985
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<volume>
					4
				</volume>
				<issue>
					1
				</issue>
				<fpage>
					14
				</fpage>
				<lpage>
					17
				</lpage>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/optnumlangs.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						Comment on an article by Jean Laponce in the same issue of the journal. Laponce describes two benefits and five costs associated with linguistic multiplicity, suggesting that on balance the welfare of the world's public would be enhanced if the world were unilingual. But Laponce has omitted some important considerations that make linguistic diversity economical. They include the continuing effort required for the maintenance of linguistic uniformity, the functional specialization of languages, the possibility of targeted partial language learning, the non-additivity and possibly even subtractivity of the costs of learning multiple languages, and the existence of languages designed for second-language mastery.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			research-article
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<journal-meta>
				<journal-title>
					Rationality and Society
				</journal-title>
				<abbrev-journal-title>
					Ration Soc
				</abbrev-journal-title>
				<issn>
					1043-4631
				</issn>
				<publisher>
					<publisher-name>
						Sage Publications
					</publisher-name>
				</publisher>
			</journal-meta>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						The World Language Problem
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<month>
						1
					</month>
					<year>
						1991
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<volume>
					3
				</volume>
				<issue>
					1
				</issue>
				<fpage>
					78
				</fpage>
				<lpage>
					105
				</lpage>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/worldlangprob.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						Antagonists in the ancient controversy over world multilingualism agree that a successful artificial language must overcome a coordination problem: to motivate learners when few speak the language. It is believed a take-off point must be reached, after which the spread of such a language would be self-sustaining. This problem may also frustrate other linguistic and nonlinguistic innovations. The dynamics of recruitment and defection, however, render a take-off point analysis dubious. A simple model of artificial-language evolution supports this doubt. Despite low learning cost, universal competence in an artificial language, if achieved, might be unstable. More generally, any degree of penetration by an artificial language, from 0% to 100% of the world population, might be stable. The results help interpret the fact that the artificial language movement is small yet stable, frustrated yet complacent, and convinced that language choice is a social dilemma that needs coordination to prevent a deficient outcome.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			research-article
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<journal-meta>
				<journal-title>
					Law and Society Review
				</journal-title>
				<abbrev-journal-title>
					Law &amp; Soc'y Rev.
				</abbrev-journal-title>
				<issn>
					0023-9216
				</issn>
				<publisher>
					<publisher-name>
						John Wiley &amp; Sons
					</publisher-name>
				</publisher>
			</journal-meta>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						The Impact of a Legal Revolution in Rural Turkey
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Starr
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								June
							</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<month>
						6
					</month>
					<year>
						1974
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<volume>
					8
				</volume>
				<fpage>
					533
				</fpage>
				<lpage>
					560
				</lpage>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/legalrev-abs.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						When the Shari’a courts of Turkey were abolished in 1924, the judiciary became legally independent of religious control. The replacement of the Shari’a by the Swiss civil code in 1926 abolished the jurisdiction of Islamic law in family relations.
					</p>
					<p>
						The Turkish revolution in legal codes and legal institutions was ambitious. Rural masses resisted dealing with agents of the central government and giving up the rule of the Shari’a and/or local customary law.
					</p>
					<p>
						Three years (1965 through 1967) of the docket of the Middle Criminal Court in the town of Bodrum, however, suggests that the Turkish legal revolution is a revolution in more than form. Rural Turks are using the courts, not just being brought into court by the government. Most cases, in fact, are civil ones. The use of the courts by citizens extends to arenas formerly within the sphere of religious law alone: These are now among the most common kinds of cases. Women, a traditionally deprived group, are increasingly turning to the court to redress grievances, in some ways more efficaciously than men. At least in its treatment of women and debtors, we find evidence that the court is not merely reinforcing the traditional power structure or serving as an instrument for governmental control of the population.
					</p>
					<p>
						The government, however, does use the courts for control. The village	case volume data in the Bodrum docket attest to the penetration of central authority into rural Turkey.
					</p>
					<p>
						Whether this central control is state control or party control has been debated, and our data show abrupt shifts in governmental prosecution and judicial decision patterns. The precipitousness and the timing of these changes suggest that Turkish courts are subject to, and are transmitters of, changing influences as national inter-party transfers of political power take place.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			research-article
		</article-type>
	</article>
</articles>
