<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--based on Google Scholar template technical-report-with-abstract.xml-->
<articles xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<article>
		<front>
			<publisher>
				<publisher-name>
					Utilika Foundation
				</publisher-name>
				<publisher-loc>
					Berkeley, California, USA
				</publisher-loc>
			</publisher>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Ambiguity Control in Human-Machine Multiagent Systems: State of the Art
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<year>
						2004
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/ambigmas.html">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						A survey of efforts to solve problems of linguistic ambiguity in the development of increasingly global and agent-supported information systems. Ambiguity is a central obstacle to several requirements for successful communication in multiagent systems. Strategies for dealing with this obstacle include controlling (preventing) ambiguity, and resolving it. Control strategies are present in many traditional and recent disciplines regulating the use of natural and formal languages. Conditions (such as the cost of misunderstanding and the relative value of the time of the communicating parties) are enumerated that would be expected to determine whether control or resolution strategies are more effective.
					</p>
					<p>
						Ambiguity control can be distinguished by whether it is central or distributed, and by whether it controls semantic or structural ambiguity. Semantic ambiguity tends to be domain-specific and structural ambiguity domain-independent. Central systems tend to be more efficient with domain-independent problems. Thus systems that employ central control of structural ambiguity and distributed control of semantic ambiguity are plausible. Formal languages, interactive elicitation systems, and controlled natural languages are among the devices with which control of structural ambiguity during the production of utterances has been attempted. Predicate-logic-equivalent varieties of natural languages, some equipped with checking tools, have purportedly been able to represent large fractions of the meanings humans want to express, but this claim requires verification, and such languages also require users to learn that the sole denotations of their expressions are not always the most probable denotations of the same expressions in the languages from which they are derived. The concept of multilingual equivalent controlled languages remains almost unexplored. Further research could be fruitful on the human factors in the usability of controlled natural languages and other strategies of ambiguity control.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			technical-report
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<publisher>
				<publisher-name>
					Utilika Foundation
				</publisher-name>
				<publisher-loc>
					Berkeley, California, USA
				</publisher-loc>
			</publisher>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Ambiguity: Some Bibliographical Notes
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<day>
						5
					</day>
					<month>
						6
					</month>
					<year>
						2005
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/ambib.html">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						Annotated bibliography of works on ambiguity. Works are classified by subtopic into these categories: concepts of ambiguity; universal and contingent ambiguities; dimensions, types, and relatives of ambiguity; and controlling ambiguity.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			technical-report
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<publisher>
				<publisher-name>
					Utilika Foundation
				</publisher-name>
				<publisher-loc>
					Berkeley, California, USA
				</publisher-loc>
			</publisher>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Web-Scale Expressivity and Ambiguity in a Translation Interlingua: The DLT Intermediate Language 
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<day>
						2
					</day>
					<month>
						4
					</month>
					<year>
						2007
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/ambigcl/evdlt.html">
				</self-uri>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/ambigcl/evdlt.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						An exploration of 32 controlled natural languages, based on English and eight other languages, revealed one, the DLT Intermediate Language, that was designed for multidomain use and whose documentation gave sufficient instructions and examples to allow a domain author to translate a realistic range of Web content into it. A test of this language on a sample of sentences from Web documents in the health and human rights domains found it expressive enough to represent all sentences in the sample, with low structural ambiguity, but some structural and much semantic ambiguity remained that could interfere substantially with human and machine comprehension.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			technical-report
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<publisher>
				<publisher-name>
					Utilika Foundation
				</publisher-name>
				<publisher-loc>
					Berkeley, California, USA
				</publisher-loc>
			</publisher>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						The Panlingual Camera Phone
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Hecko
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Martin
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Ogunmola
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Kinsley
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Wong
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Tim
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Woodman
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Peter
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<month>
						3
					</month>
					<year>
						2007
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlingual.org/devpilot/rev.html">
				</self-uri>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://www.cs.washington.edu/education/courses/cse490f/07wi/project_files/camera/devpilot/rev.html">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						Progress report on the design of a user interface for an application that would operate on a mobile camera phone. Increasingly high-fidelity prototypes have been implemented on paper, on the Web, and on one mobile device, with revisions based on user and expert evaluation of the prototype on the basis of realistic tasks. The interface design provides for multimedia (camera, stored-image, text, handwriting, etc.) input with language identification, text recognition, and translation into any language, to be performed collaboratively by the user, the device, remote servers, and a human-computation network.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			technical-report
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<publisher>
				<publisher-name>
					Utilika Foundation
				</publisher-name>
				<publisher-loc>
					Berkeley, California, USA
				</publisher-loc>
			</publisher>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Panlingual Dogfood
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<year>
						2006
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/pandog/index.html">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						The idea of a linguistically diverse yet efficiently interactive world is becoming popular, but no plausible model for its realization has yet been described. I envision here a process that supports this goal with collaborative panlingual semantic standardization. The process is panlingual not only in its product but also in its operation, thus complying with the "eat your own dogfood" principle and using its product to make itself possible. It is also participatory and lexicocentric, as illustrated by "dogfood". I envision the process helping to panlingualize interactive services, including search, question answering, discussion, correspondence, and knowledge dissemination.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			technical-report
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<publisher>
				<publisher-name>
					Utilika Foundation
				</publisher-name>
				<publisher-loc>
					Berkeley, California, USA
				</publisher-loc>
			</publisher>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Paraphrasal and Truth-Conditional Disambiguation of Quantification: Which Works Better?
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<day>
						6
					</day>
					<month>
						4
					</month>
					<year>
						2007
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/aa/index.html">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						The Semantic Web vision requires authors to create unambiguous content, but whether authors are willing and able to do this even minimally has been questioned. To address this doubt, I conducted a pilot experiment. Subjects saw 25 sentences with scopally ambiguous adverbial quantifiers, such as "almost always". Subjects attempted to disambiguate each sentence by choosing between alternative representations of its possible meaning. Subjects were assigned to either or both of two tasks. In one task, each representation was a paraphrase. In the other, each representation was a situation description (a truth condition).
					</p>
					<p>
						Subjects, on average, spent about 25 seconds per sentence, exhibited about 75% inter-task consistency, chose meanings by about 75% majorities, and became faster as they got practice. The paraphrasal task was enjoyed somewhat more and was performed faster than the truth-conditional task. The most dramatic influence on speed was presentation order: Subjects performing two tasks per sentence were much faster if the paraphrasal task was first on the page than if the truth-conditional task was first. A pair of tasks in the former order was almost as fast as a single truth-conditional task. Sentences differed substantially in how difficult it was for subjects to disambiguate them consistently and consensually. The most difficult sentences were those with near-universal quantification and multiple categorical arguments and complements. Subjects also showed apparent sensitivity to the order of verb arguments, being biased by whether a cause appeared before or after its effect. Subjects' comments called attention to subtle ambiguities in the instrument and exhibited a wide range of attitudes, from excited discovery to frustrated confusion, toward the tasks.
					</p>
					<p>
						The results cast doubt on the doubt about humans as disambiguators. Both paraphrasal and truth-conditional disambiguation appear to be viable. They may also be efficiently combinable. Further research can explore task order, trainability and incentivizability for disambiguation tasks, and differences among individuals and sentences relevant to disambiguation task design.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			technical-report
		</article-type>
	</article>
	<article>
		<front>
			<publisher>
				<publisher-name>
					Institute of Mathematical Economics, Universität Bielefeld
				</publisher-name>
				<publisher-loc>
					Bielefeld, Germany
				</publisher-loc>
			</publisher>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						Ĉu Mi Lernu Esperanton? Enkonduko en la Teorion de Lingvaj Ludoj (Symmetric Equilibria in Linguistic Games)
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Selten
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Reinhard
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<month>
						3
					</month>
					<year>
						1982
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/lernesp.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						This paper, intended for an audience of activists in an international language movement and hence written in the movement's language, Esperanto, argues that they are attempting to influence the outcome of a linguistic game. In our model, the players are individuals each of whom has one native language. The players choose among strategies that consist of decisions about what other lan­guage or languages to learn. They are motivated by a desire to be able to communicate with as many other human beings as possible, but also by an aversion to the cost (time, effort, money, etc.) of learning languages. The payoff to any player from any outcome is then the difference bet­ween two quantities: (1) the communicational benefit and (2) the language-learning cost of the outcome.
					</p>
					<p>
						The model assumes the existence of an artificial language with no native speakers that has a lower general learning cost than any of the players’ native languages. We show that, in a special 2-group case, no equilibrium is possible in which everyone learns the language of the other group, nor can an equilibrium exist in which every­one learns either the other group’s language or the ar­tificial language. These impossibilities imply that, in a symmetric equilibrium where everyone learns a language, it must be the artificial one. Requirements for 4 other kinds of symmetric equilibrium are then derived.
					</p>
					<p>
						Somewhat counter-intuitive relationships exist between parameters of the game. A drop in the general learning cost of the natural languages could be expected to lead to a fall in the total number of language learners. An equal drop in the general learning cost of both the natural languages and the artificial one could be ex­pected to produce a reduction in the number of persons learning a natural language. These relationships become plau­sible when the impact of price-sensitive behavior on com­municational benefits is taken into account, given that choices among languages are dictated by both what they cost to learn and how many marginal players they bring into one’s communication network. This feature of decisions about language learning bears a resemblance to decisions about the consumption of fashionable goods.
					</p>
					<p>
						We conclude with some speculations about the extension of the analysis to asymmetric equlibria, to games with more than 2 group languages, and to games with language groups differing in size and personal learning-cost distributions. Only the latter extension appears likely to cause a major change in the conclusions reached here, and it could signifi­cantly add to our understanding of linguistic inequality.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			technical-report
		</article-type>
	</article>
</articles>
