<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--based on Google Scholar template thesis-with-abstract.xml-->
<articles xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<article>
		<front>
			<publisher>
				<publisher-name>
					Department of Government, Harvard College
				</publisher-name>
				<publisher-loc>
					Cambridge, Massachusetts, USA
				</publisher-loc>
			</publisher>
			<article-meta>
				<title-group>
					<article-title>
						The Usefulness of Quantitative Methods in Political Science: The Case of Scaling and the United States Supreme Court
					</article-title>
				</title-group>
				<contrib-group>
					<contrib contrib-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>
								Pool
							</surname>
							<given-names>
								Jonathan Robert
							</given-names>
						</name>
					</contrib>
				</contrib-group>
				<pub-date pub-type="pub">
					<month>
						3
					</month>
					<year>
						1964
					</year>
				</pub-date>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/scaling.pdf">
				</self-uri>
				<self-uri xlink:href="http://panlex.org/pubs/etc/scaling.txt">
				</self-uri>
				<abstract>
					<p>
						Part IV of a Harvard College B.A. honors thesis in government. The theory and practice of Guttman scaling as a method for the analysis of votes cast by justices of the United States Supreme Court, by Glendon Schubert and others, is described and evaluated, with note taken of critiques by Wallace Mendelson and others. The method is found to be capable of significant contributions to objective description, pattern discovery, and hypothesis formulation. It has been used in general analysis of judicial behavior and in the discovery of the principles underlying voting by particular justices, especially Felix Frankfurter. But it is also found to have been the source of unwarrantedly aggressive conclusions, particularly when applied to collections of cases spanning periods of time long enough to be accompanied by changes in the court's membership and/or exhibiting missing votes. In some terms, e.g. 1934 and 1961, there are enough general unidimensionality and missing votes to make all cases in the term scalable, in which case it is questionable whether the scalability of any discretionarily selected subset of cases dealing with a particular issue provides evidence for the justices' selection of that issue as the basis for their votes. Promising combinations of Guttman scaling with other kinds of analysis, including by Harold Spaeth and Joel Grossman, are discussed.
					</p>
				</abstract>
			</article-meta>
		</front>
		<article-type>
			ba-thesis
		</article-type>
	</article>
</articles>
